Southern Tenant Farmers Union Records on Microfilm 5204 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- January 1957 to December 1957, Undated 1957, and January 1958 to March 1958. (Reel 40)
  - January to March, 1957, 1 (Reel 40)
    The negotiations with the Amalgamated Meat Cutters over the proposed merger may be followed through Mitchell's correspondence with Galarza and with Patrick Gorman throughout the winter. In the middle of February, the AFL-CIO Industrial Union Council granted the NAWU $25,000 for a special program to obtain the enforcement of P.L. 78, which stated that domestic workers should have job preference over foreign nationals in farm work. See the exchange between Mitchell and Walter Reuther on the grant (Feb. 18, 21), as well as Mitchell to Galarza on his recent conversation with Victor Reuther, who explained the internal AFL-CIO politics responsible for the grant (March 8). There is a letter from Mitchell to AFL-CIO Secretary-Treasurer William F. Schnitzler on the latest developments in the dispute with UPWA (March 14), and a report by Galarza on his conversation with UPWA President Ralph Helstein (March 22). The Nineteenth Convention was held in Memphis on March 30; the papers include the full proceedings and the Report of the Executive Board
  - April to June, 1957, 2 (Reel 40)
    The jurisdictional dispute between the NAWU and UPWA over sugar workers began to heat up; see especially the exchange between Mitchell and Rev. Louis J. Twomey of Loyola University (April 5, 10), the angry exchange between Mitchell and UPWA Vice-President A.T. "Tony" Stephens (June 5,11,16), and the report of the NAWU Louisiana organizing staff on their meeting with Stephens (June 20). There are also two letters from Mitchell to all sugar workers' locals directly affiliated with AFL- CIO, suggesting that they join a proposed autonomous department within NAWU (April 15; May 17), and a letter from Mitchell to Galarza on his trip to Louisiana and the strawberry farmers (May 5). Finally, there is a statement by Mitchell to the House Judiciary Sub-Committee on the recent importation of Japanese farm workers into California (May 16)
  - July to September, 1957, 3 (Reel 40)
    The dispute with UPWA over Louisiana sugar workers continued through the summer; see especially Mitchell to William Schnitzler, with attached correspondence relating to the dispute (July 10) and the frequent exchanges of letters between Mitchell and Galarza during September on UPWA and on California organizing plans in general. In his effort to publicize the plight of domestic farm workers under the bracero system, Galarza focused on a group of 100 families at a Yuba City government camp desperately in need of relief. There are several items relating to the Yuba City poverty beginning on August 8 and continuing to the end of the month; see also Galarza's mimeographed report on conditions in Sutter County (Sept 16). The papers include the transcripts of hearings held by the House Judiciary Committee during May on the importation of Japanese farm workers in to the United States (Aug 27, Sept 11); among the witnesses are C.B. Rhodes, Manager of the North California Farm Labor Association, and Edward F. Hayes, Chief of the US Farm Placement Service. The union renewed its organizing efforts among New Jersey chicken farmers and Louisiana strawberry growers. On the chicken farmers, see Mitchell to his brother "Little Boy", giving him instructions on how to set up the American Poultry Farmers Co-operative Association (July 5); on the NAWU's work with strawberry farmers, see Mitchell to Robert Senser, Associate Editor of Work (July 29).
  - October to November, 1957, 4 (Reel 40)
    During the last week of October, the leaders of the United Sugar Workers, Local 1422, decided to disaffiliate with the NAWU and return to UPWA. From October 26 on, the papers are primarily concerned with Mitchell's attempt to stem the revolt by placing the local in receivership and by sending organizer George Stith to Louisiana to win the support of the rank-and-file membership. The key documents include Galarza's report on his trip to Louisiana to appraise the situation (Nov 10), Stith's reports (Nov 21 to 27), and Mitchell's memorandum on the role of UPWA in the revolt (Nov 14). There is a set of notes by Galarza on a meeting of the Regional Labor Operations Advisory Committee of the US Bureau of Employment Security held in San Francisco (Oct 31), a copy of the Proceedings of the NSF Conference on Migratory Labor and Low Income Farmers (Nov 13) and a letter from Mitchell to Walter P. Reuther, stating that the NAWU will not consider a merger with UPWA as Reuther had apparently suggested (Nov. 5)
  - December, 1957, 5 (Reel 40)
    The reader may follow the progress of the attempt to re-organize Sugar Workers Local 1422 through the frequent reports of George Stith (3 to 14). There is a series of letters from Galarza to California Governor Goodwin J. Knight on specific violations of the US-Mexican International Agreement in the San Joaquin Valley (3 to 7); see also the reply from H.W. Stewart, Director of the California State Department of Employment (16). At the AFL-CIO Annual Convention in Atlantic City, Frank P. Graham called together a group of high-level labor leaders and proceeded to lecture them on the importance of organizing agricultural workers. Dr. Graham's talk inspired A. Philip Randolph, Leon Schachter, and ILGWU Vice-President Charles S. Zimmerman to write a memorandum to Walter P. Reuther proposing a survey on the prospects for organizing farm labor (12); see also Mitchell's account of the meeting in his letter to Father Donald McDonnell (17)
  - No Date, 1957, 6 (Reel 40)
    Several memoranda by Mitchell on NAWU organizing plans; "Facts and figures", a report on the size and structure of NAWU; NSF report on "The Condition of Farm Workers in 1957"
  - January and February, 1958, 7 (Reel 40)
    Plans developed rapidly for the survey proposed to Walter Reuther in December; see the memoranda by Mitchell and by the ad hoc committee to Reuther (Jan 6, 18), and Mitchell to Galarza on his conversation with Victor Reuther about the study (Feb 4). With the aid of Congressman James Roosevelt, the union attempted to obtain a Congressional investigation of alleged racketeering in the Mexican labor import program; for information on this campaign, see especially Galarza to Mitchell (Jan. 19), Mitchell to Nelson Cruikshank (Jan. 28), and an NAWU press release and memorandum on the proposed investigation (Feb. 17). There is a statement by NAWU organizer Raul M. Aguilar, who was refused work by an employer after being referred by the local Farm Placement Office (Jan 17), and two memoranda by Galarza on future organizing plans in California (Jan 28, Feb 27). On the continuing dispute with UPWA, see the formal NAWU complaint filed before the AFL-CIO No-Raiding Impartial Umpire (Jan 23), the correspondence between Mitchell and organizer George Stith on UPWA activity among Louisiana sugar workers, and Mitchell to Walter P. Reuther on the dispute (Feb 22)
  - March, 1958, 8 (Reel 40)
    The papers include a number of letters from Galarza on his fight to obtain enforcement of P.L. 78 by USES and the California State Farm Placement Service; see also the letters to Congressman John F. Shelley from USES Director Robert C. Goodwin and California Regional Director Glenn Brockway on the work of the Regional Foreign Labor Operations Advisory Committee in California (7, 14). Mitchell met with AFL-CIO Secretary-Treasurer William F. Schnitzler on March 25 to attempt to work out a compromise with UPWA; see his eight-page memorandum on the record of the negotiations with UPWA and his reports on the Schnitzler meeting to Galarza and to the NAWU Executive Board (25, 31). Finally, there is an interesting exchange between Mitchell and former NAWU organizer Henry Pelet on the Louisiana sugar situation (20, 24).
- April 1958 to December 1958, Undated 1958, and Miscellaneous Union Business 1958. (Reel 41)
  - April and May, 1958, 1 (Reel 41)
    Due to Congressional pressure, the Department of Labor became more sensitive to NAWU demands to eliminate the abuses of the Labor Import Program. Mitchell met with officials of the Bureau of Employment Security at the beginning of Aril and during a somewhat stormy session of Labor's Advisory Committee on Farm Labor at the end of May; the papers include Mitchell's report to Galarza on the first meeting (April 10), a letter from BES Deputy Director E.L. Keenan on the proposals drawn up at the meeting (April 14), Galarza's criticism of those proposals (April 16, 19), and a memorandum on what took place at the meeting in May (May 27). See also Mitchell's letter to Congressman John F. Shelley charging that the minutes of the Regional Foreign Labor Operations Advisory Committee which Shelley had procured revealed a conspiracy between the BES and the large California growers (April 17). There is an eleven-page report by Galarza on his work during the past year to force the BES to provide jobs for domestic workers in California (April 17)
  - June and July, 1958, 2 (Reel 41)
    Mitchell spent the first part of the summer in California inspecting farm labor conditions; for details on what he found, see his highly pessimistic letters to Fay Bennett and Gardner Jackson (July 25, 30). Before he left for the West, Mitchell delivered a lengthy statement to the House Agriculture Committee opposing plans to make the Mexican Farm Labor Importation Program permanent (June 11). In the course of his testimony, Mitchell charged that California governor Goodwin J. Knight, then up for re-election, was involved in a shady deal involving Mexican farm workers; see Galarza's letters on the impact these charges had in California (June 13, 16) and letters from Gardner Jackson and David A. Munro on their efforts to obtain a signed statement on the charges from Mitchell's source of information (July 14, 17, 28). During this summer, the union conducted an "experiment", operating a labor supply program in conjunction with the Pennsylvania Farmers Association; for information on this venture, see the correspondence with the Association and with organizer George Stith throughout the summer
  - August to October, 1958, 3 (Reel 41)
    On Mitchell's trip to California, see his lengthy report to the NAWU Executive Board (Sept. 18) and his exchange with BES Director Robert C. Goodwin (Aug. 1, 8). Galarza, meanwhile, had become involved in the intense political campaign underway in California; the papers include a press release charging Governor Knight with duplicity in his policies toward agricultural workers (Aug. 20) and various items relating to the campaign to defeat Proposition 18, described as a Right-to-Work Law in disguise (Aug. 10; n.d. [Oct]). There is an NSF press release on the formation of a new National Advisory Committee on Farm Labor (Oct. 20), and a long letter from Frank L. Noakes, Chairman of the US Section, Joint US-Mexican Trade Union Committee, to Secretary of Labor Mitchell protesting the lack of compliance machinery in the Mexican Labor Import Program (Aug. 29)
  - November and December, 1958, 4 (Reel 41)
    The activities of the NAWU came to a virtual halt during these two months as the union waited to see what kind of support the AFL-CIO might grant. On the financial crisis, see especially the exchanges between Mitchell and NSF Executive Secretary Fay Bennett (Nov 12, 14), Walter Pl. Reuther (Nov 17, Dec 2), and A. Philip Randolph (Dec 2,5). There is a six-page letter from Galarza on his winter plans in California (Nov. 13), and a letter of equal length from Mitchell to broadcaster Edward P. Morgan on the problems of American farm labor (Dec. 3)
  - No Date, 1958, 5 (Reel 41)
    A letter from the Bureau of Employment Security providing statistical information on the farm labor recruitment program; two memoranda by Mitchell on setting up the National Advisory Committee on Farm Labor; "A Proposal For Organization of Agricultural and Allied Workers in Louisiana"; report by Galarza on foreign nationals in California; "Why Farmers Need a Union" by H. L. Mitchell
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1958, 6 (Reel 41)
    Folder 1540-B -- Correspondence with the Union Life Insurance Co. and with NAWU accountant A. Benjamin Hall. Folder 1540-C -- Correspondence with the AFL-CIO Industrial Union Department on per capita tax payments, and correspondence with local secretaries on dues payments. Folders 1540-D and -E -- Not Filmed.
- January 1959 to August 1959. (Reel 42)
  - January and February, 1959, 1 (Reel 42)
    On January 8, Mitchell met with George Meany, Walter Reuther, A. Philip Randolph, and Leon Schachter to formulate an AFL- CIO program for the organization of farm labor; the papers include a memorandum by Mitchell which gives a full account of the meeting (Jan. 8). On February 5 and 6, the National Advisory Committee on Farm Labor held widely-publicized hearings in Washington; the papers include statements by Mitchell, Galarza, NAWU organizers George Stith and Raul Aguilar, and California peach worker Delmer Berg, speeches by John M. Seabrook, President of Seabrook Farms, and AFL-CIO Secretary-Treasurer William Schnitzler, an illustrated NAWU booklet entitled "The Blight on the Countryside", and a 40-page "Report on Farm Labor" issued by the Committee (Feb. 5 and 6). There are five different sets of minutes of BES Advisory Committee meetings called to discuss the new set of regulations for farm labor recruitment proposed by the Department of Labor (Jan 27; Feb 9, 10, 11, 28). The American Farm Bureau Federation, alarmed by all this activity, sent out a report of its own to its state affiliates on the Advisory Committee hearings and the BES meetings (Feb 13). There is a letter from Mitchell to historian Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. on the account of the STFU which appears in Schlesinger's The Coming of the New Deal (Jan 26), and a set of letters from Mitchell to state officials in New York, New Jersey, and Pennsylvania, offering to supply their states with southern farm workers during the coming summer (Feb 13)
  - March and April, 1959, 2 (Reel 42)
    On the new AFL-CIO campaign to organize California farm workers, see Mitchell's letters to Galarza (March 26, April 3) and the position paper issued by the AFL-CIO entitled "An AFL-CIO Program to End Nineteenth Century Poverty in Twentieth Century America" (n.d. [April]). On the proposed revision of BES regulations governing the recruitment of domestic farm labor, see the Advisory Committee reports on the "Current Situation Relating to Proposed Regulations" (March 3) and Mitchell's letter to the Secretary of Labor, praising the new regulations but saying they do not go far enough (March 30). There is a memorandum from Mitchell to Walter Reuther on organizing Puerto Rican and Southern migrant farm workers (April 8), and a number of statements and press releases from the US Section, Joint US-Mexican Trade Union Committee (April 6,15,28)
  - May, 1959, 3 (Reel 42)
    The AFL-CIO Agricultural Workers Organizing Committee (AWOC) began its work in California uner the direction of former UAW organizer Norman Smith. There is a great deal of information on the progress of the AWOC in Mitchell's correspondence with Smith and Galarza throughout the summer; see also the agreement between NAWU and UPWA on jurisdiction over the workers organized by AWOC (21), and the letters from Mitchell to various AFL-CIO state labor councils asking them to circulate petitions among farm workers calling on the AFL-CIO for help in organizing (13). There is an exchange between Mitchell and Assistant Secretary of Labor Newell Brown on Mitchell's complaints that the BES is anti-union (1, 19), a memorandum from Leon Schachter to the AFL-CIO Industrial Union Department requesting assistance in organizing migrant farm workers in the Northeast (18), and a memorandum from Mitchell to NSF on plans for the union's 25th Anniversary celebration (25)
  - June, 1959, 4 (Reel 42)
    On the AWOC, see the frequent exchange of correspondence between Mitchell and both AWOC Director Norman Smith and Ernesto Galarza, as well as the minutes of an AWOC meeting (14). Two of Mitchell's letters to Smith and Galarza contain considerable information on the progress of the NAWU attempt to interest the AFL-CIO in a similar organizing campaign in the East (8,11). There is a memorandum by Mitchell to Senator Harrison A. Williams, Jr. on extending social welfare legislation to farm workers (4), and a joint letter to Smith and Galarza on NAWU strategy concerning the forthcoming hearings by Senator John F. Kennedy's Welfare and Labor Committee on minimum wages for farm labor (26). The papers also include a BES memorandum on "Procedures and Requirements -- Mexican Labor Program" (17)
  - July and August, 1959, 5 (Reel 42)
    The AWOC organizing campaign continued in California; see Galarza's five-page mimeographed letter to the Director of the California State Department of Employment detailing his complaints with the Department (July 7), and two AWOC Research Papers on "The Future Disposition of Public Law 78" and "The Wages that Prevail" (July 30; Aug 19). There is an interesting exchange between Mitchell and the Secretary of Labor over the NAWU charge that various state farm placement services are corrupt (Aug 5, 14, 18), and another exchange between Mitchell and Aurbrey Williams over Mitchell's request that Williams use his influence with Lyndon B. Johnson to convince Johnson to sponsor farm labor legislation (Aug 10, 21). There are letters from both NAWU lawyer Daniel H. Pollitt and Mitchell to Fred Blackwell, Counsel of the Senate Committee on Labor and Welfare, providing him with background information for the hearings to be conducted by the Sub-Committee on Migratory Labor (Aug 18,19), as well as a letter from Mitchell to Otto Feinstein of the University of Chicago reviewing the NAWU's relations with Mexican trade unions (Aug 24).
- September 1959 to December 1959, Undated 1959, Miscellaneous Union Business 1959, and January 1960 to May 1960. (Reel 43)
  - September, 1959, 1 (Reel 43)
    Along with the plans for the 25th Anniversary celebration, the importation of British West Indian farm workers into New York and New Jersey becomes the dominant issue in the papers this month. On this subject, see Mitchell's letter of complaint to the Department of Labor, see Mitchell's letter of complaint to the Department of Labor (1), a reply from New Jersey Governor Robert Meyner (10), a 17-page WDL report on "The Plight of the British West Indian and Bahamian Migrants" (28), and a letter from New Jersey Senator Harrison A. Williams, Jr. on his committee's planned investigation of migratory labor (5). The Department of Labor held hearings on the migrant problem; the papers include statements from the NAWU (2), the AWOC (9), and from the US Section, Joint US-Mexican Trade Union Committee (10). Finally, there is a copy of an NAWU resolution adopted by the Third AFL-CIO Convention on "Hired Farm Labor and Imported Contract Workers" (18)
  - October, 1959, 2 (Reel 43)
    A one-day celebration on October 17 commemorated the 25th Anniversary of the NAWU; the papers include a speech by Albert Whitehouse, Director of the AFL-CIO Industrial Union Department (17). There are two highly informative letters from Mitchell to Galarza summing up his impressions of the AWOC organizing campaign during his recent visit to California (3, 27), as well as several letters from Galarza on his complaint that the workers recruited by AWOC were all being sent into UPWA (22, 24, 28). There is an exchange between William T. O'Rear, Secretary of the Fresno (Calif.) Central Labor Council, and Mitchell on arranging a mass meeting of farm workers in Fresno in early December (12, 15, 28)
  - November and December, 1959, 3 (Reel 43)
    The dispute between the NAWU and UPWA concerning jurisdiction over the workers organized by the AWOC continued; see especially Mitchell's letters to Galarza and NSF Executive Secretary Fay Bennett on his talks with AFL-CIO officials on the problem (Nov 23) and Galarza's report on the AWOC campaign (Nov 6). On Mitchell's plans to set up a Southern AWOC, see his long letter to Dr. Frank A. Graham (Nov 27) and his draft of "A Program to Organize Southern Agricultural Workers" (n.d. [Nov]). There is a letter from Mitchell to Galarza on his conversation with Fred Blackwell, Council to Senator Harrison Williams' Sub-Committee on Migratory Labor, concerning the Committee's forthcoming hearings (Nov 24) and a memorandum by Galarza prepared to assist Blackwell (Nov 30). The papers also include an exchange between Mitchell and James W. Patton, Director of the Southern Historical Collection, on bringing the STFU Papers to Chapel Hill (Nov 30, Dec 8), and an unpublished article by Priscilla Roberson, written in 1937, on the life of Myrtle Lawrence, an Arkansas sharecropper and STFU member (Nov 3)
  - No date, 1959, 4 (Reel 43)
    "Data on Hired Farm Labor", a report by Clay L. Cochran of the AFL-CIO Industrial Union Department staff; AWOC leaflets; magazine article by Mitchell, "Farming is Big Business"; article, "The Voice of the Disinherited: A Brief History of the Agricultural Workers Union, 1934-1959"; "A Program for Organizing Hired Farm Workers in the South"; "Draft of a Proposed Program on Hired Farm Labor"; report by Mitchell on "Operations of the National Sharecroppers Fund, Inc."; Report of the New York State joint Legislative Committee on Migrant Labor"; three letters for H. Clay East, first President of the STFU; "List of Persons Available to Carry Out Union Job Placement Program"
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1959, 5 (Reel 43)
    Folders 1573a and 1573b -- Routine correspondence with the Union Life Insurance Co., with local secretaries, etc. Folders 1573c to 1573g -- Not Filmed
  - January to March, 1960, 6 (Reel 43)
    A sudden crisis developed when Mitchell was informed by Walter Reuther that the AFL-CIO was about to revoke the NAWU's charter. As Mitchell and Galarza soon learned, the NAWU was caught in an internal AFL-CIO political battle between Reuther and George Meany, which involved the Amalgamated Meat Cutters and the UPWA as well. Fortunately, Mitchell typed up detailed memoranda after each of the crucial meeting held during the crisis; the papers include memoranda on Mitchell's conversations with Reuther include memoranda on Mitchell's conversations with Reuther and A. Philip Randolph (Jan 6), with the AMC and UPWA over a possible merger with NAWU (Jan 19), with Victor Reuther (Jan 25), with Walter Reuther again (Feb 25), with George Meany (March 3), and with AWOC Director Norman Smith (March 9). Mitchell's 12- page statement to the NAWU National Advisory Council provides an overview of the sequence of events (n.d. [March])
  - April and May, 1960, 7 (Reel 43)